A Guide to the Papers of the Town Reversion Committee, 1927-1999 (bulk 1995-1999)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Town Reversion Committee 1927-1999 (bulk 1995-1999)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11602, -a
This collection consists of ca.1,200 items in 9 Hollinger boxes, 3 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library by Catherine Peaslee, Lloyd Smith, William Lucy, Garrett Smith, Robert McNergney, and the Town Reversion Committee, all from Charlottesville, Virginia, in March and April of 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Core members of the Town Reversion Committee included William Lucy, Robert McNergney, Catherine Peaslee, James Self, Lloyd Smith, and John Wheeler. Their primary attorney was Garrett Smith.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of the Town Reversion Committee, 1927-1999 (bulk 1995-1999) (ca.1,200 items in 9 Hollinger boxes, 3 linear feet) and includes reversion court proceedings, correspondence, clippings, research, and financial records.
The papers detail the efforts of the Town Reversion Committee to change the City of Charlottesville's status from a city to a town. Virginia is the only state in which cities are independent from the counties in which they are located. The practice arises from early in the Commonwealth's history according to the rationale that rural and urban people should have separate governing structures. The process of urbanization was managed through annexation, until the 1980s when large counties became exempt from it.
By reverting to town status, the City of Charlottesville would have become part of Albemarle County, which would in turn have become responsible for providing Charlottesville's services and resources. The move would have pooled the revenue bases of the city and Albemarle County, in a sense subordinating the city to county, but leaving Charlottesville with an independent governing authority in its own name. Reversion to town status was the main tool the city had to change its status because the process was launched by the city and decided by the court. County officials would be a party to drawing up the specific terms of reversion ultimately recommended by the court --a panel of three judges appointed for the task by the Virginia Supreme Court-- but the county could not stop the process. The city, however, could withdraw the reversion appeal if it decided the terms offered by the court were not to its liking.
The Town Reversion Committee was formed in 1995 and subsequently petitioned the City of Charlottesville to take action to revert to town status. From 1996-1997 the issue was heard in the Circuit Courts of Charlottesville, and then in 1998 the issue was appealed to the Supreme Court of Virginia, which placed a moratorium on reversion to town status by any of Virginia's independent cities. The Town Reversion Committee disbanded in 1999 after losing support from the Charlottesville City Council.
Box 2 contains additional background research on reversion and the City of Charlottesville including city procedural guidelines, publications, reports and data. It also contains a video of the Board of Supervisors' hearing on reversion with notes taken at the actual hearing. Also, Charlottesville City Council documents including information on the Democratic Committee members, candidate information for the 1998 city council election, and other miscellaneous papers.
Box 3 contains correspondence regarding the reversion issue from the Town Reversion Committee, the Town Reversion Committee's lawyers, Clarence McClymonds, Catherine Peaslee, and Lloyd Smith.
Box 4 contains the court proceedings from the Circuit Court of the City of Charlottesville including briefs, memoranda, and a typed copy of the hearing proceedings. It also contains the beginning of the Supreme Court of Virginia court proceedings of The City of Charlottesville v. The County of Albemarle.
Box 5 contains Supreme Court proceedings from The City of Charlottesville v. The County of Albemarle including briefs and appendices of authorities.
Box 6 contains the remainder of the City of Charlottesville v. The County of Albemarle Supreme Court proceedings, which is the three volume appeal pleadings index. Also, it includes the Town Reversion Committee's financial records, including bank statements, deposit slips, information on individuals that donated to the committee, lawyer's bills, and other miscellaneous bills and records.
Box 7 contains a copy of the original reversion petition, database information on the petition and individuals who signed it, individuals who wanted to be removed from it, and miscellaneous materials such as maps, notes, and petition handouts. Also, it contains the Proposed Terms for Town Reversion by Five Petitioners, and the beginning of the exhibits that accompanied it.
Box 8 contains the remainder of the exhibits that accompanied the Proposed Terms for Town Reversion. Also, it contains reversion publicity including advertisement, newspaper and magazine clippings, information from forums that were held, information sheets that were handed out, mailings, and press releases.
Box 9 contains Town Reversion Committee documents including information of the members of the committee, the conceived structure of the committee, and the minutes from all Town Reversion Committee meetings. It also includes writings on reversion including letters to the editor, and reports and talks that were given on reversion.
Arrangement
This collection is organized alphabetically by subject matter, and then chronologically within folders.
Contents List
- Background Information: Case Studies: Petitions 1927-1996 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Background Information: Case Studies: Reversion 1948-1984 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Background Information: Case Studies: Reversion 1987-1995, n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Background Information: Case Studies: Schools 1991-1997 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Background Information: Code Sections n.d. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Background Information: History of Incorporation n.d. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Background Information: Law Reports n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Background Information: Procedural Guidelines 1987-1996 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Background Information: Publications 1990-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Background Information: Reports and Data: misc. [1990-1997] (Box-folder 2:3)
- Background Information: Reports and Data: reversion c.1995 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Background Information: Reports and Data: schools n.d. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Board of Supervisors Hearing 1997 Jan 3 (Box-folder 2:6)
- City Council: Democratic Committee Information n.d. (Box-folder 2:7)
- City Council: Election, 1998 1998 (Box-folder 2:8)
- City Council: Miscellaneous Papers [1995-1999] (Box-folder 2:9)
- Correspondence: Lawyers' 1996-1997 Apr 14 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Correspondence: Lawyers' 1997 Apr 17-Jun (Box-folder 3:2)
- Correspondence: Lawyers' 1997 Jul- Dec (Box-folder 3:3)
- Correspondence: Lawyers' 1998 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Correspondence: Lawyers' 1999 Jan- Nov 17 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Correspondence: Lawyers' 1999 Nov 18- Dec (Box-folder 3:6)
- Correspondence: Clarence McClymonds 1996 Nov-1997 Sep (Box-folder 3:7)
- Correspondence: Catherine Peaslee 1996 July-1999 Dec (Box-folder 3:8)
- Correspondence: Lloyd Smith 1996 Dec-1999 Mar (Box-folder 3:9)
- Correspondence: Town Reversion Committee 1996 Oct-1999 Aug, n.d. (Box-folder 3:10)
- Court Proceedings: Attorney's notes n.d. (Box-folder 4:1)
- Court Proceedings: Charlottesville City Court [1996-1997] (Box-folder 4:2)
  (folder 1 of 4)
- Court Proceedings: Charlottesville City Court [1996-1997] (Box-folder 4:3)
  (folder 2 of 4)
- Court Proceedings: Charlottesville City Court [1996-1997] (Box-folder 4:4)
  (folder 3 of 4)
- Court Proceedings: Charlottesville City Court [1997-1999] (Box-folder 4:5)
  (folder 4 of 4)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court [1996-1997] (Box-folder 4:6)
  (folder 1 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court [1998] (Box-folder 4:7)
  (folder 2 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court 1998 May-Oct (Box-folder 5:1)
  (folder 3 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court [1998] (Box-folder 5:2)
  (folder 4 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court 1998 (Box-folder 5:3)
  (folder 5 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court [1998] (Box-folder 5:4)
  (folder 6 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court [1998] (Box-folder 5:5)
  (folder 7 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court 1998 Jan-1999 Jan (Box-folder 6:1)
  (folder 8 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court 1996 Nov-1999 Jun (Box-folder 6:2)
  (folder 9 of 10)
- Court Proceedings: State Supreme Court 1996 Nov -1999 Jun (Box-folder 6:3)
  (folder 10 of 10)
- Financial Records: Bank Statements 1996-2000 (Box-folder 6:4)
- Financial Records: Deposit Slips 1996-1998 (Box-folder 6:5)
- Financial Records: Donation Information 1997, n.d. (Box-folder 6:6)
- Financial Records: Lawyers' Fees 1996-1999 (Box-folder 6:7)
- Financial Records: Miscellaneous [1996-1999] (Box-folder 6:8)
- Petition [1996] (Box-folder 7:1)
- Petition: Database Information 1997 Jun 13 (Box-folder 7:2)
- Petition: Miscellaneous Materials [1995-1996] (Box-folder 7:3)
- Petition: Names and Information Alphabetically 1997 May 12 (Box-folder 7:4)
- Petition: Names and Information by Sheet 1997 (Box-folder 7:5)
- Petition: Signature Withdrawals 1997 (Box-folder 7:6)
- Proposed Terms for Town Reversion 1996 Nov-Dec (Box-folder 7:7)
- Proposed Terms for Town Reversion: Exhibits 1-12 [1996 Dec] (Box-folder 7:8)
- Proposed Terms for Town Reversion: Exhibits 13-26 [1996 Dec] (Box-folder 8:1)
- Proposed Terms for Town Reversion: Exhibits 27-38 [December 1996] (Box-folder 8:2)
- Publicity: Advertisements 1995-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 8:3)
- Publicity: Clippings 1990-1996 (Box-folder 8:4)
- Publicity: Clippings 1997 Jan-Jul (Box-folder 8:5)
- Publicity: Clippings 1997 Aug-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 8:6)
- Publicity: Forums 1991-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 8:7)
- Publicity: Information Sheets and Pamphlets n.d. (Box-folder 8:8)
- Publicity: Mailings 1997 Jan-1998 Mar, n.d. (Box-folder 8:9)
- Press Releases 1995-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 8:10)
- Town Reversion Committee: Member Information and Committee Structure c.1996-1997 (Box-folder 9:1)
- Town Reversion Committee: Minutes 1996 May-1999Aug (Box-folder 9:2)
- Writings: Letters to the Editor 1992-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 9:3)
- Writings: Talks and Reports on Reversion 1996-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 9:4)